Lawsuit Claims Big Problem With Popular Arizona Iced Tea Flavor
Ginseng is rare, expensive, and takes a long time to mature.
But a 23-fluid-ounce (680 ml) can of Arizona Iced Tea's "Green Tea with Ginseng and Honey" only costs 99 cents or less.
If you feel something's not quite adding up here, you're not alone.
As reported in the agricultural magazine Modern Farmer, a new lawsuit claims that the drink contains no detectable ginseng.
According to the suit, filed in New York, three separate lab tests could detect no ginseng in the Arizona Iced Tea.
But they did detect ginseng in two competing tea products that claim to include ginseng.
If it succeeds, the lawsuit could force the Arizona Iced Tea company to change the labeling for the drink, which the beverage company claims, is the "best-selling green tea" in the US.
Currently, the label has "ginseng extract" second-to-last on its list of ingredients, which are listed from most to least plentiful.
The tea also claims to contain "ginseng for energy."
The ginseng root, which is commonly found in China and South Korea but is also grown in the US, has been used in traditional Chinese medicine for thousands of years.
It is said to have all sorts of health benefits and typically sells for $50 per pound (.45 kilograms) for the cultivated version. Wild ginseng can go for as high as a thousand bucks per pound.
The lawsuit was filed by two consumers and seeks class-action status to represent anyone who has purchased the tea.
The article points out that McDonald's was once successfully sued for $5 million over just two slices of cheese.